Finding Aid for Robby DeBoer Papers, 1977-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robby DeBoer Papers 1977-2006, 1991-2006
DeBoer, Robby, 1957-
1 oversize folders
20 linear feet
2010188 Aa 2; UAl
Two year custody battle over "Baby Girl Clausen" between Jan and Robby DeBoer of Ann Arbor, Michigan and her biological parents Cara Clausen and Daniel Schmidt of Blairstown, Iowa; and the national child advocacy group Hear My Voice. The collection consists of correspondence, news clippings, press releases, photographs, audio cassette tapes, CD-ROMs, DVDs, video tapes, and legal papers such as petitions, briefs, judicial orders, and amicus briefs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Robby DeBoer (donor no. 10367 ) in June 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The custody battle over "Baby Girl Clausen" began shortly after Cara Clausen gave birth to the baby girl on February 8, 1991 in Cedar Rapids, Iowa. Two days after giving birth, Cara Clausen signed a "Release of Custody," releasing her parental rights to "Baby Girl Clausen." At the same time, she named Scott Seefeldt, her current boyfriend, as the father of the baby. Like Clausen, Seefeldt also signed a "Release of Custody" of the child. On February 25, 1991, The Juvenile Court of Linn County, Iowa terminated the parental rights of Cara Clausen and Scott Seefeldt and named Jan and Roberta "Robby" DeBoer of Ann Arbor, Michigan as the legal custodians of "Baby Girl Clausen." On the same day, Jan and Robby DeBoer filed a petition in the District Court of Linn County, Iowa to adopt the baby. By March 1, 1991, "Baby Girl Clausen," had moved into her Ann Arbor, Michigan home with Jan and Robby DeBoer. The couple named the baby Jessica.
On February 28th, Clausen changed her mind about the adoption and informed the real father of the baby, Dan Schmidt, of the child. By March 6, 1991, Clausen had filed a "Request to Revoke and Vacate Orders" with the Juvenile Court of Linn County, Iowa and an Affidavit stating that she did not identify the real father, claiming now that Daniel Schmidt was the actual biological father to "Baby Girl Clausen."
On March 21, 1991, the Juvenile Court of Linn County, Iowa held a hearing to consider Cara Clausen's request that the court should reinstate her parental rights. The Court rejected the claims of Cara Clausen and Daniel Schmidt, holding that it no longer had jurisdiction because the DeBoers had already filed an adoption petition in District Court.
On March 27th, 1991, Daniel petitioned for custody of the baby on the grounds that he had not signed a release for the adoption as the father of the infant. The DeBoers challenged the petition in court for two years in both Iowa and Michigan. Finally, the United States Supreme Court refused to hear the case, upholding a lower-court decision giving custody of Jessica to the birth parents, who had in the meantime married and given birth to another child.
On August 2, 1993, in front of the news media, Jessica was transferred from her home with the DeBoers to her birth parents in Iowa. Jessica DeBoer is now known as Anna Schmidt.
Robby DeBoer's experience with the "Baby Jessica Case," as it was commonly known in the media, led her to establish the child advocacy group Hear My Voice. The organization, formed in Ann Arbor, Michigan, offers pro bono help for adoptive/custodial parents and guardians involved in difficult custody cases.
The Robby DeBoer papers document the legal battle and media coverage surrounding the adoption of "Baby Girl Clausen," and also the organizational records of the national child advocacy group Hear My Voice. The collection consists of correspondence, news clippings, press releases, photographs, audio cassette tapes, CD-ROMs, DVDs, video tapes, and legal papers such as petitions, briefs, judicial orders, and amicus briefs. The collection has the following series: Biographical, Litigation, Hear My Voice, Publicity, Audio/Visual Materials, and General Correspondence.
Subjects:
Adoption--Law and legislation--United States.; Adoptive parents--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Children's rights--United States.; DeBoer, Robby, 1957-; Hear My Voice.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Adoption--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Children's rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Judicial proceedings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; DeBoer, Robby, 1957-; Hear My Voice.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.; Publicity.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series documents the custody battle over Jessica from Robby DeBoer's point of view. The series includes drafts of DeBoer's autobiography Losing Jessica as well as tape transcripts where Robby DeBoer gives a detailed account of her two year fight to keep Jessica.
  - Losing Jessica, Drafts, 1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Robby DeBoer tape transcripts undated (Box 1)
- Litigation, In the Matter of Baby Girl Clausen, Roberta and Jan DeBoer vs. Daniel Schmidt
  The Litigation, in the matter of Baby Girl Clausen, Roberta and Jan DeBoers vs. Daniel Schmidt series documents the two year custody case of Baby Jessica in the Iowa and Michigan courts. The series consists of legal papers such as petitions, briefs, judicial orders, and amicus briefs.
  - Adoption Papers January-February 1991 (Box 1)
  - Court Transcripts
    - Tape transcripts, undated (Box 1)
    - Iowa District Court in and for Linn County
      - 11/4/1992 (Box 1)
    - Circuit Court for the Washtenaw County
      - 1/5/1993 (Box 1)
      - 1/26/1993 (Box 1)
      - 1/28/1993 (Box 1)
      - 1/29/1993 (Box 1)
      - 2/1/1993 (Box 2)
      - 2/2/1993 (Box 2)
      - 2/3/1993 (Box 2)
      - 2/8/1993 (Box 2)
      - 2/9/1993 (Box 2)
      - 2/10/1993 (Box 2)
      - 2/12/1993 (Box 2)
      - 4/15/1993 (Box 2)
  - Custody Laws Research 1990s (Box 2)
  - Daniel Schmidt Legal Papers 1977-1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Petitions, Appeals, Correspondence, and Other Papers
    - Iowa Courts
      - March 1991-November 1992, 21 folders (Box 3)
    - Michigan Courts
      - December 1992-January 1993, 12 folders (Box 3)
      - January-July 1993, 21 folders (Box 4)
  - United States Supreme Court September 1993 (Box 4)
- Hear My Voice
  The Hear My Voice series contains the organizational records of the national child advocacy group. The series consists of by-laws, memos, correspondence, press releases, newsletters, financial papers, and legal papers related to individual custody lawsuits supported by the organization.
  - Board of Directors
    - Memos and documentation (Box 5)
    - Minutes 1995-2006 (Box 5)
  - Bylaws (Box 5)
  - Case intake form (Box 5)
  - Chapters
    - Arkansas (Box 5)
    - California (Box 5)
    - Colorado (Box 5)
    - Connecticut (Box 5)
    - Delaware (Box 5)
    - Florida (Box 5)
    - Georgia (Box 5)
    - Illinois (Box 5)
    - Indiana (Box 5)
    - Iowa (Box 5)
    - Kentucky (Box 5)
    - Maine (Box 5)
    - Maryland (Box 5)
    - Massachusetts (Box 5)
    - Michigan (Box 5)
    - Nevada (Box 5)
    - New Hampshire (Box 5)
    - New Jersey (Box 5)
    - New Mexico (Box 5)
    - New York (Box 5)
    - North Carolina (Box 5)
    - Ohio (Box 5)
    - Oklahoma (Box 5)
    - Pennsylvania (Box 5)
    - South Carolina (Box 5)
    - Texas (Box 5)
    - Virginia (Box 5)
    - Wisconsin (Box 5)
  - Child custody case summaries (Box 5)
  - Child custody cases
    - Badilla, Antonio 2005 (Michigan) (Box 5)
    - Baldanza, Cameron and Brandon 1994 (New York) (Box 5)
    - Bauer, Monica and Rossi, Zachary 1993-1994 (Pennsylvania) (Box 5)
    - Carr, Dyron 1994 (North Carolina) (Box 5)
    - Cromwell, LADH and PPH 2006 (Michigan) (Box 5)
      See also Holey, Liliandra and Pearl
    - Dawson, Alexander 2005-2006 (Michigan) (Box 5)
    - Engels, Summer 1994 (Minnesota) (Box 5)
    - Evers, Hannah 2003 (Alabama) (Box 5)
    - Failla, Kelsey 1991-1994 (Michigan) (Box 5)
    - Frazer, Samantha 1998 (Delaware) (Box 5)
    - Gawronski, Joseph Samuel 1996-2000 (Alabama) (Box 6)
    - Gibson-Newberry, Mercedes and Keely 2006 (Michigan) (Box 6)
    - Grabarkiewicz, Gage 1994 (Michigan) (Box 6)
    - Green, Antwon 1994-1997 (Michigan) (Box 6)
    - Grissom; Rachel, Tony, and Rebecca 1994 (Missouri) (Box 6)
    - Guy, Ruby 1998 (Delaware) (Box 6)
    - Hayden, Sarah 1996 (Florida) (Box 6)
    - Heidt, Alyssa 1993 (Nevada) (Box 6)
    - Helms, Lance 1994-1995 (California) (Box 6)
    - Holey, Liliandra and Pearl 2003 (Michigan) (Box 6)
      See also Cromwell, LADH and PPH
    - Ireland, Maranda 1994-1995 (Michigan) (Box 6)
    - Janikova, Richard 1995 (Illinois) (Box 6)
    - Johnson, Michael; White, Mark, and Matthew 1993 (Texas) (Box 6)
    - Kalua'u, Kalei 1996 (Hawaii) (Box 6)
    - Kerr, Nicole 1994-2001 (Michigan/Ottawa) (Box 6)
    - King, Charles 1996 (Utah) (Box 6)
    - Lehr, Kayla 1994 (Pennsylvania) (Box 6)
    - Long, Justin Lee 1993 (California) (Box 6)
    - Meade, Stephanie 1994 (Michigan) (Box 6)
    - Medina-Bookert, Kassem 1995 (New Mexico) (Box 7)
    - Meldrum, Timothy Jr. 1998-2003 (South Dakota) (Box 7)
    - Melander, Cheyanne 1997 (New York) (Box 7)
    - Mole, Abigail 1998 (Wisconsin) (Box 7)
    - Moore, Justin 1999-2000 (Ohio) (Box 7)
    - Moores, Carrie 1993 (Ontario) (Box 7)
    - Palmer, Shala 1995 (Michigan) (Box 7)
    - Pixley, Cornilous 1997-1998 (Maryland) (Box 7)
    - Ramon, Alexander 1994 (Michigan) (Box 7)
    - Red Shirt, Cody Cavett 1994 (Colorado) (Box 7)
    - Ruiz, Lucy and Bridget 1994-1997 (California) (Box 7)
    - Schlaepfer, Felicia and Natasha 1993-1995 (Texas/Minnesota) (Box 7)
    - Scott, Daryl 1997 (Michigan) (Box 7)
    - Scott, Evan 2003-2006 (Florida) (Box 7)
    - Schwind, Megan 1993-1994 (Kansas) (Box 7)
    - Sickinger, Dillon and Taylor 1992-1997 (New York) (Box 7)
    - Simonitch, Ashlee and Nicholas 1996-1998 (Kansas) (Box 7)
    - Smith, Kyle 1996 (Texas) (Box 7)
    - Thomas, Seth 1992-1994 (Kansas) (Box 7)
    - Tipton, Donnie 1997 (Alabama) (Box 7)
    - Ventinner, Lenny 1994 (Texas) (Box 8)
    - Washington, Myokra and Tiffany 1995 (Wisconsin) (Box 8)
    - Welsh, Emily 1994-1995 (Florida) (Box 8)
    - Williams; Jonathan, David, and Clifford 1994 (Michigan) (Box 8)
    - Zalinsky, Josie and Riley, Nick 1997 (West Virginia) (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous cases and court documents (Box 8)
  - Conferences, Seminars, Events
    - 1st National Conference October 8-10, 1993 (Box 8)
    - Rally for Children's Rights October 23, 1993 (Box 8)
    - National Working Conference on Children's Rights September 30-October 2, 1994 (Box 8)
    - Educational Conference about Realities September 27-October 1, 1995 (Box 8)
    - National Training Seminar October 27-29, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Combined Federal Campaign 1996 (Box 8)
    - Defending Children First: A Call to Action October 3-6, 1996 (Box 8)
    - Building Blocks to Advocacy September 26-28, 1997 (Box 8)
    - Hear My Voice at Five Years National Conference October 2-4, 1998 (Box 8)
    - Seventh Annual Fall Conference October 8-10, 1999 (Box 8)
    - "Champions for Children" fundraising event October 16, 2002 (Box 8)
      (photographs from and recording of the event can be found in the Audio/Visual Materials series)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Contacts: includes donor correspondence and mailing lists (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1993-2004, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Financial contracts (Box 8)
  - Financial reports 1993-2005 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Hotline messages 1997-1998 (Box 8)
  - Legislation
    - National
      - Adoption and foster care (Box 8)
      - Adoption and Safe Families Act (Box 8)
    - State Laws
      - Abuse and neglect (Box 9)
      - Adoption (Box 9)
      - Adoption and Safe Families Act implementation, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Paternity (Box 9)
  - Licensing and incorporation documents 1993 (Box 9)
  - Mailings 1993-2006, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - Newsletters 1993-2007 (Box 10)
  - Press conference January 21, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Procedural handbook 1999 (Box 10)
  - Publications (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Clippings, mostly miscellaneous 1990-1998, 9 folders (Box 10)
    - Documents and other publications, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Pins undated (Box 10)
- Publicity
  The Publicity series reflects the media interest in the custody battle between Jan and Robby DeBoer and Cara Clausen and Daniel Schmidt. The series is made up of news clippings, writings about the custody case, and the script from the television movie based on the custody battle. The series also contains the papers from the support group Justice for Jessi, which later became the Jessica DeBoer Committee for Children's Rights.
  - Clippings, mostly DeBoer 1973-2003, 13 folders (Box 11)
  - The DeBoer Dilemma University of Michigan Law School Bridge Week, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Interview Requests and Correspondence 1993 (Box 11)
  - Justice for Jessi Committee 1993 (Box 11)
  - Press Releases 1993 (Box 11)
  - Prime Time Live viewer correspondence, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Whose Child is This? The War for Baby Jessica, Script, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Writings and Articles 1993-1994 (Box 11)
  - Posters and event announcements (Folder UAl)
- Audio/Visual Materials
  The Audio/Visual Materials series contains the following subseries: Audio Cassette Tapes, CD-ROM/DVD, Photographs, and Video Tapes.
  - Audio Cassette Tapes
    The Audio Cassette Tapes subseries contains music recordings made in support of the DeBoer's adoption of Jessica as well as a radio broadcast on the Illinois Chapter of Hear My Voice.
    - Annie Rose
      - "Do You Feel It: Special Edition Release for The DeBoer Committee for Children's Rights 1993 (Box 12)
      - "Hear My Voice: Justice for Jessi DeBoer and Children in Crisis Everywhere," 1993 (Box 12)
    - Hear My Voice, Illinois Chapter, WJJG-AM 1530 Live Radio Broadcast 1997 (Box 12)
  - CD-ROM / DVD
    The CD-ROM/DVD subseries contains recordings of events and conferences associated with Hear My Voice.
    - "Can you Hear the Children's Voices?," undated, 2 optical disks DVDs (Box 12)
    - "Champions for Children" fundraising event (Box 12)
    - Hear My Voice Conference 1999 (Box 12)
      (audio recording only)
    - Hear My Voice Kids, slide show undated (Box 12)
    - "Smile: Start Making it Livable for Everyone," Oakland County Circuit Court 2006, 2 optical disks DVDs (Box 12)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries consists of images of Hear My Voice events. The subseries also contains two images of Jessica DeBoer/Anna Schmidt; one image is of Jessica when she was two years old and still living with the DeBoers, the second image is of Anna Schmidt as a teenager.
    - "Champions for Children" fundraising event 2002, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Child Abuse Reform Legislation, Press Conference 1997 (Box 12)
    - Hear My Voice
      - Conference (Ann Arbor, MI) 1998 (Box 12)
      - Snapshots of Families and Children 1990s-2000s (Box 12)
    - Jessica DeBoer/Anna Schmidt 1993, 2000s, 2 photographs (Box 12)
    - KABC-Radio's Dennis Prager Rally for Baby Richard 1995 (Box 12)
    - Rally on Washington and the Baby DeBoer fund 1992 (Box 12)
  - Videotapes
    The Videotapes subseries includes recordings of television news segments covering the Baby Jessica Case, other custody cases between adoptive and biological parents, and Hear My Voice events. The video recordings on the Jessica DeBoer case illustrate the extent to which the custody case captured the nation's attention. The recordings include news segments from national media outlets as well as local news stations. Tape 43 is notable because it shows Robby and Jan DeBoer receiving training to assist them with answering questions during the many high profile interviews they conducted during the two year custody case.
    - Jessica DeBoer
      - Tape 1: WJBK Detroit January 1992 (Box 12)
      - Tape 2: TV2 News October 1992 (Box 12)
      - Tape 3: 20/20; Local News Segments, 1992-1993 (Box 12)
      - Tape 4: TV2 News; Good Morning America, January 1993 (Box 12)
      - Tape 5: Good Morning America, January-February 1993 (Box 13)
      - Tape 6: Good Morning America, January, April, August 1993 (Box 13)
      - Tape 7-14: "Schmidt vs. DeBoer," Court TV February 1993, 8 tapes (Box 13)
      - Tape 15: 20/20, March 1993 (Box 13)
      - Tape 16: Justice for Jessi Rally April 1993 (Box 13)
      - Tape 17-18: Justice for Jessi Rights Rally in D.C. July 1993, 2 tapes (Box 13)
      - Tape 19: Good Morning America, July 1993 (Box 13)
      - Tape 20: WDIV-TV Detroit August 1993 (Box 13)
      - Tape 21: NBC News Now, August 1993 (Box 13)
      - Tape 22: "Jessica: The Final Hours," KGAN-TV August 1993 (Box 13)
      - Tape 23: George Rogers Clark High School Support Video October 1993 (Box 14)
      - Tape 24-25: American Journal, circa 1993, 2 tapes (Box 14)
      - Tape 26: Rally in Washington 1993 (Box 14)
      - Tape 27: Whose Child is This? The War for Baby Jessica, 1993 (Box 14)
      - Tape 28: NBC News Now, July 1994 (Box 14)
      - Tape 29-30: DeBoer Interviews October 1994, 2 tapes; beta tapes (Box 14)
      - Tape 31: 48 Hours, 1994 (Box 14)
      - Tape 32: The Crusaders, 1994 (Box 14)
      - Tape 33: PrimeTime Live, 1994 (Box 14)
      - Tape 34: NBC News NOW 1994 (Box 14)
      - Tape 35: WDIV-TV Detroit 1999 (Box 14)
      - Tape 36: Comparisons to Elian Gonzalez Good Morning America, NBC Today Show, Fox TV News, 2000 (Box 14)
      - Tape 37: "What ever happened to Baby Jessica," WDIV 2003 (Box 14)
      - Tape 38: Can You Hear?, undated (Box 14)
      - Tape 39: CBS This Morning undated (Box 14)
      - Tape 40-41: DeBoer Committee for Children's Rights undated, 2 tapes (Box 14)
      - Tape 42: Jan DeBoer Interview, MSNBC undated (Box 15)
      - Tape 43: Robby and Jan DeBoer, Interview Training undated (Box 15)
    - Other Custody Cases
      - Tape 44: Atkins, Josh (Ohio) undated (Box 15)
      - Tape 45-46: Baby Richard undated, 2 tapes; beta tapes (Box 15)
      - Tape 47: Mankin, Allyson 1996 (Box 15)
      - Tape 48-49: Meldrum, Timothy Jr. (South Dakota) 2001-2002, 2 tapes (Box 15)
      - Tape 50-51: Moore, Justin (Ohio) 1999-2002, 3 tapes (Box 15)
      - Tape 52: Raub, Paula and Hawk (Washington) circa 2000 (Box 15)
      - Tape 53: Simonitch, Ashlee and Nicholas (Kansas) undated (Box 15)
      - Tape 54: Smith, Lily and Pearl (Michigan) circa 2000 (Box 15)
      - Tape 55: Birth Parent Rights Discussion March 1993 (Box 15)
      - Tape 56: "Listen to the Children," Family Law Section of the State of Michigan Bar March 1993 (Box 15)
      - Tape 57: "The Long Journey Home," 20/20, December 1992 (Box 15)
      - Tape 58: "Why Don't Kids Have a Voice?" ABC News Special 2001 (Box 15)
    - Hear My Voice Events
      - Tape 59-61: Drake Hotel/Ali Event October 2002, 3 tapes (Box 15)
      - Tape 62: First Annual Children's Rights Benefit Dinner November 1993 (Box 15)
- General Correspondence
  The General Correspondence series is comprised of letters received, mainly in the period of April-November 1993. The letters are from citizens throughout the United States and some foreign countries in response to the "Baby Jessica" case. Most of the letters are supportive of the DeBoers, seeking more information, asking how they might help, providing some monetary support, etc. There are no letters sent in response. The letters are unarranged.
  - Letters received, April-November 1993 (Box 16)
  - Letters received, April-November 1993 (Box 17)
    (continued)
  - Letters received, April-November 1993 (Box 18)
  - Letters received, April-November 1993 (Box 19)
  - Letters received, April-November 1993 (Box 20)
Related Material
The Law Library of the University of Michigan has 59 videocassettes of the coverage of the case as seen on Court TV.